I don't know if I want another
Another
>> look exactly the same.
>> Okay, I shamed them into coming to the
wrong class.
>> They don't make up
a deep learning class.
>> This is
[laughter]
going on YouTube.
>> Yes. Griffy just doesn't have enough
capacity.
>> All right, good morning everybody and
I'm stolen for time because I'm hoping
that the actual microphone that allows
me
here but uh I do want to thank Dr.
garage for not only getting me here and
trusting me enough to to teach today,
but uh I mean you uh took me from a
soldier who thought Python was a snake
to being semi competent in this realm.
>> That being said, I am more nervous about
teaching this than I was president or
storming any room with machine guns.
>> [clears throat]
>> So today we're going to talk about
reinforcement learning
and uh
>> introduce yourself back
>> and uh hopefully we we learn a little
along the way. I you all owe me
>> I have spared you from 380 of
someone extremely good and I will not in
any way.
So the things we'll go over today
learning you know one of the complex
problems that reinforcement learning is
briefly the timeline
[clears throat] reinforcement learning
and how it's
how it's evolved uh over uh since
inception.
I'll have the microphone in.
>> Uh then we're going to talk um in depth
about the Marov decision process which
is really the the building block that
everything uh in reinforcement learning
is built on.
We'll go on to uh dynamic programming,
model free reinforcement learning,
function approximation and deep
reinforcement learning and then
reinforcement learning through human
feedback. My personal favorite and the
thing I've messed up the most. Uh then
we'll discuss the limitations and open
problems around reinforcement learning
and uh then I'll open it up for
questions.
So, first of all, why reinforcement
learning? Why why do we use this?
>> We have these amazing
absolutely everything.
>> We're really good at our classification
problems. Well, sometimes real uh
problems.
>> Hi, brother.
>> The voice is very very low. You can't
hear well.
>> My voice is very low. Yeah, we're
waiting on the
>> Yes. Very very
>> speak.
[laughter]
>> All right. Um so uh reinforcement
learning is is good for these sequential
uh decision making tasks. Uh whereas
supervised learning is is really
designed for these static data sets and
reinforcement learning allows us to
learn via interaction.
child and since two we made it the goal
that she one day be a high-powered CEO
and despite me every morning trying
different loss functions I'm not able to
have her wake up and just be a CEO so uh
I don't want to resort to spanking or
anything like that but we've tried RLu
we've tried Sigmoid anybody have any
suggestions we'll move on So,
what if we break it down into a a bigger
pack?
Two years old, she goes to her first day
of school. Three years old, uh, she
enrolls in Carnegie Melon.
I'll give her till 18 for her first job
at NASA. And then, uh, hopefully by 20
she can run Nvidia and
take up the mantle.
But we don't know if that's the the best
path there. Uh, you know, do I need to
to find out that at three she turns to a
life of crime so that she can get that
street cred that uh really helps you out
on Wall Street? Uh, spend a little time
in prison, uh, developing contacts,
um, and then hopefully not making the
absolute worst decision of all like her
father and joining the army.
Well, all of what we're going to learn
today is going to end up being an
evolution of this one equation, the the
uh policy optimization and the the
principle of optimality.
Um,
and while it might look like there's a
lot going on right there, we're going to
see through this that it's it's a pretty
simple equation and that there are
different ways that we can attack it. It
looks like my microphone has paired up
just in time. So, we'll take a quick
break while I get that.
You never
Zoom. Can you guys hear me better now?
>> Very very much.
>> Excellent. And now I don't have to to
stand right behind the scary podium. Uh
so uh when we talk about the timeline uh
the that very first equation that I
brought up the the Bellman equation that
uh came around between 1949 and uh it
was iterated on until 1957 by brilliant
mathematician Bellman. Uh then in 1970s
and 1980s we went on to tabular exact
methods and dynamic programming.
uh in 1980s everybody's favorite uh
Monte Carlo uh simulations came into
popularity and we all love that because
it's just throwing as much data in there
as possible and hoping something good
happens. Um then in 1988 uh Sutton came
up with temporal difference learning
allowing us to in inject that a little
more of a time element into that. uh in
' 89 uh Q-learning uh and uh some of the
model free uh methods began to uh pop
up. Uh 1990s into 2000 function
approximation.
Uh in 2013
we started seeing uh deep reinforcement
learning with the rise of neural
networks and uh in uh 2015 we saw kind
of a a resurgence in these policy
gradient methods. But perhaps the
biggest development in reinforcement
learning was from deep mind in 2016.
uh and we'll go over that in depth uh
through the slides. Uh in 2015 to 17 we
were seeing trust region and uh stable
policy methods. Right now we're we're
going through a modelbased reinforcement
learning resurgence and uh also in 2018
we started to see uh uh reinforcement
learning through human feedback. And one
of the things that uh you'll see is the
way this has all evolved over the years
is kind of in line with the advancement
of hardware. As uh things have
developed, the intractable have become
tractable and we've been able to do more
math in a more efficient way and it's
allowed us to to explore reinforcement
learning more in more depth.
So now I'm going to do what my hero does
and go to the board uh and we'll we'll
introduce the problem uh that
reinforcement learning looks to to
solve.
So
just going to introduce a a few concepts
to you, a few key terms, but we'll all
start from our very very simple world
where our agent
is the cab
doing what every cab strives to do,
picking up passengers.
Um so a few terms that we we get from
this is our state you know where we are
uh what's the world around us right now.
So in this particular uh example, the
intersections
can end up being our states.
Uh then we go on to, you know, what's
our reward? You know, what do we what do
we want? And
if I was driving a cab, I think money
which comes from that passenger is going
to be the thing that we're trying to
get. Another concept is the cost. What
does it take for us to get to that
reward? Uh in this particular case, it
could be the amount of gas that uh you
move going from one intersection to the
next. It can be uh the amount of wear
and tear on your vehicle, especially if
you're here in Pittsburgh and the
potholes are bigger than they should be.
Uh and um then we have our objective.
You know, anyone want to guess at the
objective here?
Man, that's a lot of blank stairs. Y'all
creep me out.
>> Pick up the person. pick up the person
kind of what we want to do. We said we
want to get that reward, but so we want
the reward
as high as we can get
and the cost
as low as we can get. So we're
maximizing that through our objective.
Uh so
that's the the base setup of the problem
we're going to uh iterate on all day
today. So if this was if this sucked,
it's all going to suck. [laughter]
So the story so far that feels good to
say.
though uh the state at in this case we
go with the the nodes the intersections
the reward get that money the cost what
it takes for us to move between those
intersections and the objective maximize
that reward minimize that cost
very very simple so far um but
let's change gears and instead of just
being
the one cab. What if we are the cab
company and we have our lovely cabs all
over the place?
Um, how do we know what cab to send to
any given passenger at any given node?
we have to have some kind of of way of
evaluating uh what these what's the
value of each one of these states. Uh so
in in particular we we can look at it as
a maze problem and go all right well you
know I'm I'm three spots away but that
implies that we have some agency here uh
as we've all tried to use a cab. Well
maybe your kids now with Uber andyft
have not had to deal with this. Uh Lord
knows where they're going. It's
completely random. So,
while we may send this cab, which has a
third of a chance per cost of getting to
that objective, it also has
2/3 of a chance. No, one two of going
away from our target because we have no
agency in this decision. It's the the
cabbie with all the the agency. So we
can use that exact math to define the
value of any given one of these nodes.
So here it was 1/3 2/3 uh with a a cost
of one. You know here we can end up
going
uh you know it has a 50/50 chance of
getting closer and 50/50 of going
farther away. That makes sense.
And uh what we'll use here for that that
value um is is just a part of the
Bellman equation. From any one of these
we can understand the total value by
using it and all the other nodes in a uh
recursive equation u to get the value of
each one of those nodes. We also want to
bring up a concept here uh called a
marovian system. Uh so in a marovian
system you need only the information of
your state to make any further action.
So here by knowing all right we're in
state two we have that one-third chance
of of getting to the reward a twothird
chance of getting away from the reward.
This can become non-marovian
if we end up needing more information.
If there's something crazy happening and
we need to take that into account now
all of a sudden we it's not part of the
state. It's to something totally
different non-marovian. But what I'm
going to bring up next will show that we
can actually take these things and make
them uh marovian once we get a little
creative. So uh to uh iterate on that
like I need a slide person. [laughter]
Uh so here we we talked about the no
agency model uh the Bellman equation as
it it works for this uh value function
and uh we brought up the marovian
system. So now we're going to bring up
uh a concept of
>> you don't have USB.
>> No, of course not. That would be way too
easy, right? Um
>> so
uh we'll bring up something called the
information state and what this is going
to do is allow us to impose that
marovian system uh onto the world. So
what if in this particular case we said
marovian system all I need is the
knowledge of my state. Well, what if I
say, well, you know, the cabs really
don't like to reverse. Uh, so
they cannot double back. Now, all of a
sudden, that is not part of our state.
We said our state is what node we're at,
right? 1 2 3. The value is our chances
of moving on. But that
uh by rephrasing this problem and and
instead of using our physical state, we
use our information state, we'll be able
to uh reimpose that marovian model onto
uh our our problem. So, anyone have any
ideas how we could take advantage of
that? How we could use that? what what a
new state could look like if we wanted
to incorporate the rule like no
backtracking
>> direction of heading
>> what was that
>> the direction at which the cab is
heading
>> as part of the state
we could do that what um
I I would propose something a little
simpler uh because
But kind of an iteration on exactly
that. So
what if instead of 1 through nine these
states become something like all right
if the cab
is moved from here to here uh it it
becomes in state
65 which precisely what you said you
know where did it come from to where did
it get but [clears throat] now we know
all right instead of like here where it
has these uh four edges that it can go
in any one of those directions. Uh now
it has uh different edges. You know 65
would connect to what 58
and one last one to see if anybody's
paying attention. What's our last state?
>> Boom. See they do pay attention.
>> [laughter]
>> Uh so with this we see that with enough
creativity we can actually model our
world as marovian uh and use that
principle in order to uh do
reinforcement learning as a whole. We
can re-encode that that information into
our state so that from our state we have
enough information to act on.
So from that we uh we discussed
information states uh we talked about
reframing a state so that we can model
the world through a a marovian model.
All right. Everything we've talked to
about so far has uh given us absolutely
no agency. It's pure probability of
whether we'll move from one state to the
next. Um but let's let's introduce a new
concept is we actually get to uh have
some agency. You know, we get to decide
what's what's some uh what's the best
move from here. um and and we get to
make that decision. But in order to make
that decision, we need to be able to uh
have some kind of process for that. And
that we're going to call that the
Marovian decision process.
So
from this marovian decision process what
we'll end up doing
is use those values that we created
earlier
uh be it you know the 1/3 2/3 with the
cost of one or the 50/50 with the cost
of two those kind of things um to decide
what is the optimal move at any given
state. Uh so we're still just using the
state to uh inform our our actions, but
we're able to create a policy uh based
on this. And where we'll see there, we
tend to want to go to wherever the uh
the next value is the best. And so some
of that on paper is extremely intuitive.
you know, every single one of you will
know, all right, if our cab is here,
what's the best move or at least which
are the best two moves, what are the
worst two moves? And so we can use that
uh to create a policy you know where uh
we always go towards you know the the
state with the highest value next or in
this case where we have two uh states
that'll likely have the exact same
value. Uh what do [clears throat] we use
as that tiebreaker? Is it a stochastic
thing? Is it uh deterministic or we
always going to choose left because
we're left-handed um or because or
always turn right because it's easier to
turn right in traffic. These things end
up becoming uh part of your policy. So,
so from there we just brought up
policies, you know, the things that you
you make these decisions into. Um, and
we'll go on from there. Now, what
happens? Everything so far has has been
talking about this uh
environment that is staying stagnant the
entire time. There's there's no change
hadn't been. But that's not how the real
world works. You know, what if now all
of a sudden we have the angry protesters
who are trying to block traffic
uh trying to to cut off our our cab
driver because they they believe that
now the the cabs need to unionize or you
know any of these real world situations
where we need to be able to model that.
But we know the protesters can't move uh
as quickly as the car. So, do we do
something like, all right, we go out of
our way to go down, uh, you know, do we
account for that environmental shift?
How do we account for these things and
how do we work that into our policy? Um,
and this is where you really need to to
understand some things that we go beyond
this pure uh deterministic, all right,
we're chasing the highest value 100% of
the time, we'll always do it this way.
And uh kind of the easiest way to
demonstrate this is going to be by me
crushing Masa in rock paper scissors.
So I've got a policy. You might guess.
Come on. You you know there you go.
But so on paper I have a one-third
chance of winning. Oh wow. You're rough
at this. Uh, I have a 1/3 chance of
winning, a one-third chance of losing,
and a onethird chance of tying.
But if I do rock every single time, I
would hope
[laughter] that Masa would learn to beat
me. The environment would understand my
actions and go, "Wow, he's really bad at
rock, paper, scissors." and from there
uh my policy would actually become
pretty worthless. So that's the easiest
way to explain why you know sometimes
you need that stochcastic element in a
decision-m process in the policy
creation because a predictable policy
with an adapting environment can
frequently become pretty worthless.
So one other thing that I should bring
up from from all that is as we're
learning these values uh and we see the
way the environment reacts,
we know a little more about what's
happening right this instant or than
what is going to happen in the far
future or uh as the world evolves, we
start to to trust what we've seen a
little less. And so that brings into
something called a discount where we we
start putting more weight on our our
current knowledge, our current state,
our current rewards than the future
state. And but keep in mind, we say the
future state, but all we've seen are the
past states. So you're not only
discounting the future, you're using
that past as that prediction of the
future. So by uh increasing your your
discount, you're saying I trust the past
significantly less. Uh if you're in my
shoes and you're over 40, I no longer
believe that the best path to being a
CEO is exactly what my parents preach.
You know, pull yourself up by your
bootstraps. you know, work hard. Like,
I'm not saying that doesn't help, but I
trust it less than I did when I was 18.
Uh, so there's more factors than that,
more variables that have been
introduced. It's not that that's wrong,
it's that it's gotten more dynamic, and
there's now more things more recently
that help shape my decisions. Hopefully,
that made sense and isn't totally
confusing because I like to be very
confusing.
So
now we while we started with this
extremely simple Bellman equation and
we're we showed how easy the math is on
our nine node uh grid.
We see how this can become pretty
ridiculously intractable very fast. So
if you start having the planning for the
entire world's taxi cabs instead of my
uh 2x two grid uh that that becomes an
very very intractable problem uh and it
requires us to know the entire world to
know how to act. So
what can we do?
Uh so first we'll we'll look back at uh
the way we address this problem and we
have our state space you know currently
we've got the the two-year-old daughter
roaring rearing to go the action space
you know what are the the uh actions
that she's going to take to get to the
next step and then we have [laughter]
the best state uh which in this case
we're going to talk about the best state
is her one day becoming that CEO uh so
her dad can retire early and never have
to worry about this stuff again. So,
so now comes into account um model free
reinforcement learning. Uh this is going
to be things like the Monte Carlo
simulation, Q-learning that you've
you've all heard so much about. What
happens when you have your grid that
we've hopefully you're all tired of by
now so I can stop coming up to the board
and you don't know what is beyond here.
You may have grown up in the city and
you'll use your priors of what you
believe the the city looks like but you
don't know. You have to act through and
learn from your actions. That's where we
get into model free reinforcement
learning. Instead of each already having
this state of, you know, 1/2 one half
uh or this policy that's predetermined,
we end up having to learn as we go. And
there's a couple ways we can do that
with uh a Monte Carlos simulation. Uh we
would do something like all right ready
go and our our agent might go here here
here
before making it there and then it looks
back and goes well was that the best way
well what would have been the absolute
best ground truth how could I have made
it which we said in three from there uh
and it'll learn from that and go wait
this was suboptimal and then it's going
to try again what if I do this
and it realizes, wow, that was even
worse. Um, and you iterate through all
these possible uh decision spaces and
use each one of those as you've
completed it to update your policy, give
new values to each of those states and
to to really understand the value of
those uh those actions. So,
so
to go over what model free reinforcement
learning is, there's no transition
model. There's no environmental
knowledge. You're learning directly from
interaction with your environment. And
uh from samples interactions, which
uh we said that that in this case would
be the sample is running through that
whole iteration seeing how that went.
Um, and so you're learning from explicit
trial and error, and you'll find that
you're alternating between policy
evaluation and policy improvement, and
it's constant bouncing back and forth
with it.
So, we just went over Monte Carlo
simulation. We're we're learning from
the full outcome. You know, there's no
evaluation at each new state. It's from
all the states that got us from our
starting state to our end state. Uh and
we observe that total return. And then
only once we have that total return and
we've completed that run do we update uh
the value estimates for those states.
So, now that we've done that, we're
absolutely going to crush it. I'll be
rich. We've learned exactly how to do
this. Very easy. We take our old
estimate, we run through and go, uh,
make a small correction and boom, done.
Uh, it's very simple. We're all going to
be rich and you all can quote me.
>> You go back to bed.
>> Yeah. [sighs] This this looks this this
looks a lot like gradient descent that
we s as the value assigning to every
state. This is what we really want to
find out and that formula over there
looks familiar, right? [clears throat]
We're looking at the square error
between
uh
G which is the actual gain that you
observed in your explorations at each
state versus the value that you've
assigned to it and you're trying to
estimate the value to minimize the
error.
>> Thank you sir.
>> Uh so why not use Monte Carlo for
everything? Um because The good things
about Monte Carlo is it will absolutely
eventually get to the right answer and
that's going to be an unbiased estimate
because we're going to have gone
completely through. But uh the bad, you
know, you can't update anything until
the end of an episode and in certain
cases that could be nearly forever. Uh
what if it it's not destined to finish?
Um this adds a lot of high variance
which returns many uh random values. Uh
if we saw there that you can end up
going in circles and not really end up
learning anything from that and so
because of that Monte Carlo is extremely
slow to converge.
Enter temporal difference learning. So,
similar to Monte Carlo, except instead
of uh running all the way from uh the
beginning to the end, what we'll do is
update immediately after each one of our
actions, we only have to go through one
or we could decide every two
intersections we're going to update. And
we see it's still extremely similar.
still updating our our value of our
state um
with a a learning rate. It's still
similar to to gradient descent like you
pointed out sir. Um and we're going to
update immediately and this is a form of
bootstrapping.
Um so when we look at this formula
though you can see something that might
be a little bit problematic.
Anyone able to point that out since it's
practically on the slide?
>> There's a tedious one on the slide.
>> Come on. I did it. I wrote it out for
you.
>> We're learning from a guess. We are
using that t + one on there to predict
t. Like, wait a minute. You you're using
the future to predict the now. Uh so we
we're injecting that bias by going wait
a minute this is how we currently
perceive the world and we're updating
how we currently perceive the world
and using that update before we even see
it. Uh so that can inject some some
serious problems. So when we look into
Monte Carlo versus temporal difference,
uh so do we wait until we know the truth
with a Monte Carlo uh simulation or uh
do we estimate the truth of the future
from our current understanding which
introduces this cascading error? You
know, if you're off by a little, you can
start diverging and end up being off by
a lot. Um, and furthermore, even if
you're not diverging a lot, you can
oscillate, go back and forth, back and
forth, retaching and unlearning the
exact same thing over and over again.
And ultimately, you end up having no
true ground truth signal like we did for
Monte Carlo.
So, how do we fix this? um in in
temporal difference learning, we were
still learning the value of those
states. Um and the problem is we still
needed that policy to act and we got
that instability with bootstrapping. But
what if we introduce a totally new
concept instead of learning the value of
a state, we learn the value of the
actions directly since ultimately that's
what we want to do is is know how to
act.
So this is going to bring up the concept
of on policy versus off policy learning.
Uh so to bring this back to to our grid,
we talk about on policy, we know we
always want to go to where we predict
the next value is going to be the
highest, always going towards our goal.
Well, we already said we don't know the
whole world. If we did know the absolute
whole world and it's unshifting then
it's just an equation we solve one done
u closed form solution. But what happens
if you know instead of there being the
one guy here we have like a super pot of
gold [laughter] up here. Uh now we would
have never learned that because it's
never in our optimal policy for us to
go out here. We know that all right
we're we're moving away from our
objective if we get here and we want to
go to the reward. We know the reward's
there. Um we move towards that. And this
is something called exploitation versus
exploration. You know, how much do we
want to introduce new information versus
taking advantage of the information we
already know? [clears throat]
So, uh two types of ways we can do this.
uh there's SARSA uh which is considered
on policy learning and then the
Q-learning which is uh a type of off
policy learning. Uh so with SARSA we
pick a random initial policy. uh we
repeatedly create episodes and for each
step in the current episode we start at
a state carry out the action get the
reward reach a new state estimate that
optimal future action and uh then we we
update the value of that action and use
through updating the value of that
action we update the current policy we
now decide if there is a pot of gold
every time I go this Okay, then perhaps
that's the better reward.
>> The problem uh with SARSA is you're
never learning from something that isn't
already in a policy. And there's there
are [clears throat] situations where
that's good. you know, if we uh happen
to be a cab driver and yes, there's a
chance that there's a pot of gold at
First and Third Street, but there's also
a pretty significant chance that uh the
Russians are invading and they chose
First and Third Street, then maybe that
risk is way too high for us to really
want to encourage exploration. We want
to go with the exploitation we already
know. I I I've already got a passenger
lined up. We're we're working towards
that instead of, you know, wait, maybe I
haven't figured out that this better
reward is out there. Um, and so brings
us back to to having to balance that uh
risk versus reward, exploration versus
exploitation.
So now we'll bring up Q-learning which
is a uh if we're going to use that
analogy is the much riskier version. Uh
you have no model required and you're
going to directly learn that optimal
behavior whether it's on policy or off
policy. So you're learning from those
decisions to go chase the pot of gold
that you didn't know was there. Uh
you're learning from the decisions that
oh man there was a tank there. um all of
this ends up adding into the your
knowledge of the value of actions and
the value of states.
So in Q-learning I I still want to point
out that while the math looks slightly
different than what we started with,
it's really the still the exact same
Bellman equation is we're looking at the
best action and we're using that that
same equation from the very very
beginning.
So why Q learning helps is uh there's no
need for a separate policy. It's it's
constantly learning uh to improve its
behavior from all of the actions it
takes
and because of that it can be pretty
quick quickly converge uh compared to on
policy learning. Um so we talk about uh
off policy you know you're you're
learning from what you actually do
learning from that exploration
uh and you're you're still going for a
target policy of what you want to learn
you know what that optimal uh lowcost
highreward situation is and Q-learning
is learning this optimal policy
eventually regardless of the behavior it
takes so
are we perfect now is this where we can
end the lecture
I know I'll be super short, but uh
probably not, right? We we still have
bootstraps
uh in this uh we tend to overestimate
the value of a a single action. And then
um it can be extremely unstable when it
comes to introducing neural networks.
And since you're all taking deep
learning, anything we learn that doesn't
uh work with neural networks is probably
going to make you ask for a refund or at
least be really upset that you had to
spend time on homework. Uh
so we move on to uh function
approximation and deep reinforcement
learning. So to talk about where we've
come from, we saw that previous methods
have have broken either because the
state space becomes uh intractably large
and so we cannot store all that [snorts]
state value in a table which is really
just straight up memorization. Um and we
need generalization. We need to be able
to uh work towards environments we
haven't yet seen.
So
uh in come the deep Q networks. So
everything we've done so far assumes
saving values in that table. Uh but
instead of a table a deep Q network uh
stores those values in a neural network.
Uh so Q-learning is is functionally
meeting neural networks there. And so
where we traditionally in the past had
those tables that learned to memorize
values, we have brought in the neural
network which now knows how to
generalize.
So in a deep Q network, it's still we're
getting back to like that super uh basic
equation. The input is that state and
the output ends up being the Q values
for each action involved with that
state.
So like we said, it's the the same
equation uh different representation.
You know, we're we're still looking up
those state action values. Uh but now
we're doing it as an approximation
instead of a direct u memorized tabular
uh value.
So now we're perfect, right? Um, we uh
took Q-learning and replaced a table
with the neural network. Nothing could
go wrong. Perfect math. Call it a day.
Except we've created this uh feedback
system which a powerful function
approximation by combining a neural
network which is nonlinear and it and
learns these global updates.
uh we've introduced bootstrapping
through temporal difference learning and
uh we're using this streaming data which
is highly correlated one decision flows
into the next uh one state into the next
you you see those transitions and what
we find is this ends up being an
extremely unstable combination.
Um so we'll address this one issue at a
time. uh correlated data. It's you're
taking sequential data uh which I like
to to think of it as your your training
data is a movie instead of the scenes
from the movie. A single picture, a
sampled screenshot. Um which if you
watch me walk across the stage, you
you'll be able to predict pretty well
what my next step is based on my
previous. it's not this this
uncorrelated data. Um and so these
similar states lead to similar updates
which ends up leading to overfitting and
poor generalization which was our whole
goal of introducing neural networks in
the first place is to get that
generalization. Uh and this is overall
creating some instability.
So our other problem is that we have a a
moving target. We're uh training a
neural network using that neural
network. So you end up running into this
thing of the network chasing itself. It
is updating itself based on its own
predictions. Uh and the target ends up
changing as it's going.
Kind of like a dog chasing its tail.
And this creates these feedback loops uh
because it's using its own predictions
and the neural network generalizes
across many states. Um so what we'll see
is any errors that we we have in this
data they're going to prop propagate
throughout and then they'll amplify uh
which leads to this massive divergence
or at best oscillation.
So to summarize, we were trying to learn
from our own guess while changing the
answer key and using highly similar
examples. Uh anyone of you who are a
data scientist would absolutely be able
to predict that that was going to fail.
So naive deep Q networks fail because
they learn from unstable targets using
that correlated data.
So is there a solution to that? Well, in
in 2015 2016, Deep Mind uh actually
worked to solve this. And it's it's kind
of genius and simple when you look at it
exactly how we did uh problem by
problem. So they took this correlated
data and they go, how can we uncorrelate
this data? Well, instead of sequentially
sampling the the steps, I can't teleport
to give a really good example. Uh but uh
we we sample and end that uh the
sequential aspect of the the training.
So this is going to stabilize training.
It's going to improve uh the the data
efficiency, how much we can learn from
any given data since we've removed that
correlation. And it allows us to reuse
the the experience. So no longer are we
training on that movie uh that
sequential film. We are sampling
different screenshots from that film and
predicting what the next would be from
that
that moving target problem. This is
going to be something that uh we we kind
of just covered with the GAN lecture is
that instead of just using our our one
neural network, we use uh a second one
and we uh use that separate network
periodically update uh each other and
they keep that target fixed for a little
while. So while you're still doing a
little bit of chasing, you've given it a
far more stable reference uh to use.
And so overall, we we see that DeepMind
didn't change Q-learning. They just
helped make it trainable. They addressed
those problems one at a time, put it
together uh and use replay to stabilize
the data and target networks to to
stabilize the objective.
So now uh are we rich? Did we make it?
Can I end the lecture? Still got 30
minutes. I'm going to be good.
Uh
well, everything we've been learning is
from these environmental rewards, but
real world tasks don't have a reward.
Uh if we wanted to have a a video game,
we we know that we're winning because we
get the high score. In robotics,
uh we know that we're doing well because
we complete the task we were assigned.
Um, but what happens?
How do we reward having your college
application to Carnegie Melon be
formatted correctly? How do we uh reward
a a very helpful review of our Nurup's
paper?
Um, and perhaps most challenging, how do
you reward a extremely creative task? If
we go and evaluate Van Gogh against AI
slop, how do we decide that that Van Go
is a better representation of what we
want than AI slop?
So, we learned that the hardest part of
reinforcement learning isn't learning,
it's defining the actual reward.
And uh so where can we come up with
these rewards?
I'm glad you liked that, Mosao. That was
all for you. Um
[laughter] we're going to use humans.
And this is where I I love being in the
army is we absolutely will throw the
most bored humans at these problems and
be like, "Good luck." Uh so the we'll
use these humans to rank outputs, give
feedback and express their preference.
Uh and this ends up becoming our reward
signal. Uh no longer this static all
right this good, that bad. It gets
correlated now with what the people
want, what what our human reviewers
want. Um so in this you're you're
replacing those environmental rewards
with human preference and you're
learning uh the reward model itself and
use that to optimize the policy. Uh we
we're essentially learning from what
humans want.
So
uh I can't iterate this enough that
absolutely nothing has changed except
where we're getting the uh reward signal
from. It's now learning uh an objective
from humans instead of uh that fixed
objective from our our algorithm.
Here's an example of RHF architecture.
it all of it can you can add very
different steps but all in all you've
got the model learning from the people
the human annotators it's a very
circular model where where it produces
its output that output gets evaluated by
people and then that's used to align the
model in the future
so the story so far uh dynamic
programming we took a a known model
model free reinforcement learning we
learned from the data uh deep RL we we
decided we're going to scale with neural
networks and then RLHF we're going to
define those rewards using humans so no
lecture would be complete without
talking about the limitations and the
open problems uh addressed by uh
reinforcement learning so our very first
problem is inefficiency we have uh
reinforcement learning wants to to uh
learn from millions of interactions.
Whereas if Masa were to decide to get me
coffee and got it way too hot, uh she
would only need to figure out one time
that, you know, she needs to use a a cup
holder or uh we've all touched a hot
stove and we know I don't need to touch
that hot stove twice to go, "All right,
I'm out. That's that's not where I want
to be. A reinforcement learning model is
not going to learn from that that one
example, at least not sufficiently.
Uh second problem is rewards are really
hard to define. And to help uh iterate
that I will bring up one of my many
failings. Um, in 2023, we decided the US
military needed to get on board with a
lot more AI use. Um, and so we decided
we were going to uh incorporate
artificial intelligence into the
targeting uh problem. You know, how fast
can we identify targets and engage
targets? And our agent was rewarded for
every target destroyed. And uh we knew
we we're smart. We know you can't blow
up everything, right? So we added a
penalty of uh when the controller says,
"Wait, wait, don't you you'll lose a
point and you'll have this 10-second
cool down until the agent can engage."
Again, what we didn't think about is
that you get the behavior you reward,
not the behavior you want. Well, all of
us can do math. If you're getting one
point per second engaging targets and
you have to wait 10 seconds to engage a
target or lose one point, it's still
more beneficial for you to continue to
engage the the targets that you've been
told explicitly not to engage. Uh so
what we found is that uh
our model completely ignored our
instructions and uh as with any good
government thing we had to deny that
that happened uh because there's no
reason to ever deny things that actually
didn't happen. Uh so
another uh problem we we brought this up
a few times today that exploration
versus exploitation. Uh how much do we
know that we are willing to explore and
how much are we willing to exploit what
we have? You know we we want to balance
that learning new things uh versus uh
doing what's safe. And this can get
really really hard to define in sparse
reward environment uh or long horizon
tasks. You know what happens when that
one person you're trying to pick up is a
100 miles away. You know now all of a
sudden you've gone very very far away
before seeing any reward and so you're
not able to to learn as much from the
the steps in between. Um so long horizon
tasks like that uh exploration and
exploitation become extremely difficult.
Uh stability and convergence I think we
hit this a few times today that we can
diverge and then we are reinforcing that
divergence and we will end up having
this uh problem that gets significantly
worse over time. uh and we can oscillate
uh we'll essentially learn nothing
because we keep correcting what we have
just learned
and this is especially true with off
policy learning like qlearn.
Uh another problem is generalization.
It's for all of us who are constantly
trying to push out papers. We see that
it's really easy to simulate data and uh
prove what we're trying to prove and
then we go out and
use that data in real life, use that
model in real life and we find that
there are a whole bunch of variables
that we did not uh account for at all.
And uh so our our problem won't
generalize from this synthetic data to
real world data. And that that can be a
big problem with reinforcement learning
where you're you're wanting to have
these millions of interactions, but it's
hard to tell your baby to run into
traffic and figure out how to cross the
street. Um because that's that kind of a
a high-risk scenario. Um you're not
going to have them cross millions of
streets so that they learn that, you
know, run across when the cars aren't
coming.
And then for our LHF, uh, our big
problem is that humans suck. Um, we are
inconsistent.
We're extremely biased. Uh, we're very
expensive because we like to eat and
have roofs over our h heads. And above
all, we're lazy. I'll bring up another
story time. In 2024, I was the newly
minted head of the uh army's natural
language processing uh unit and we did a
joint exercise with the NSA trying to
take social media data on the conflict
in Russia uh to uh do battle damage
assessments so that without using any
kind of surveillance we could see all
right is that bridge destroyed is that
tank destroyed is the city Okay. Um, and
so our our attempt was to have our
privates, uh, which we have lots of and
they're always bored and looking for fun
things to do, evaluate the output of our
model, which is looking at Twitter,
Telegram, uh, Facebook, all the social
media things, and, uh, coming up with
these this uh, battle damage assessment.
And so at first it seemed to work pretty
well. The the privates were on task.
They gave good feedback. They were like,
"Absolutely. Now I know that that bridge
is destroyed. Good job." But after a
little while, as most 18year-olds will
do, and especially when there's no
punishment for messing up, they decided,
uh, maybe it'd be funnier if we reward
the funniest output of the model. And so
we went from these very coherent battle
damage assessments to like hashtag got
them uh and uh
# you know wars up best ever all the the
best hashtags really. Um and we end up
going from a very useful product to a
completely worthless Twitter bot that uh
we should have set free on the internet
just for people to have uh laughs of. So
we see that, you know, while you're
using humans, you have to account for
human behavior. We're we're wild. You
know, we're not we're not going to give
you exactly what you want. If you ask
Masa and I to review two uh of the exact
same papers, I promise you I'll give a a
different score and my I'll probably be
a little more flippant than Mossas, and
Moses will be a lot smarter than mine.
Um and so we have to to take those
things into account uh as we're training
these models.
So let's talk about where reinforcement
learning is going. Uh we're developing
better exploration methods. We're
getting more sample efficient learning
so that we don't have to touch the stove
a thousand times. We're getting safer
reinforcement learning so that the
mistakes are not as costly. Um we're
getting better alignment. We're
understanding the way that humans behave
and so we're able to use that in RLHF
training. Um, and very recently we're
going back to world models and model
based reinforcement learning because
hardware has gotten better to the point
where now that intractable is slightly
tractable uh and and so this is uh
leading to that re resurgence.
So, a few key takeaways for the lecture.
Uh, reinforcement learning is ideal for
these multi-step tasks. Uh, we're always
going to be uh balancing exploration
versus exploitation.
And I can't emphasize this enough, the
rewards and penalties are key. Without a
good reward system and a good penalty
system, you're going to train what you
reward, not what you want.
So quick recap, reinforcement learning
is good for sequential decision-making.
Uh our big equation is that Bellman uh
recursive equation. Um model free
reinforcement learning is learning from
experience. Uh deep reinforcement
learning, we're scaling those those
methods with neural networks. And then
RLHF is where we're we're learning to
align with humans.
Hopefully with enough reinforcement
learning, my daughter one day will
become the CEO,
>> president of the United States.
>> She'd be way too mean to be president of
the United States.
[laughter]
>> So, uh, thank you. And I'm happy to take
any questions.
>> Guys, ready to take any questions about
everything that anything is discussed?
When do you know that your policy is
like sufficiently trained?
>> Do you ever know that your policy is
sufficiently?
>> You have 15 minutes and I'm convinced
that people completely confused you in
the first 15 minutes.
>> Probably
if you understood anything about the
state, the policy, the government
equation. Raise your hand. It's okay to
not raise your hand.
>> Ouch.
>> Man, I I fail.
So what exactly was the state here? This
was a city grid, right? What exactly was
the state here?
>> Mhm.
>> The intersections, right? Why did we
call them?
>> We need some way of defining.
>> Thank you.
So we need some way of defining the
world. And so uh these are our states,
right? There was a passenger to pick up
the passenger. Picking up the passenger
was a rewarding experience. He made
money. So there was a reward. Uh what
was the notion of a value
over here?
What was the notion of a value over
here?
How much reward?
>> You're going to pick up the passenger
anyhow, right? So
>> profit
>> h
>> profit. Okay, explain.
>> So like there was a cost to right pick
up the passenger and there was a reward
for picking up the passenger money. So
the difference between those two that
was
>> so from each point you're going to
travel to pick up the passenger and it's
going to cost you some amount to pick up
the passenger, right? And so
the profit that you can expect to make
if you're here versus here versus here
versus here versus here that was your
the value you associated with the state
right now how do you compute these
values
how do you compute these values
>> I'm assigning a cost to right. So let's
say the truck traveling from here to
here has a cost.
We numbered these nodes, right? One 2 3
5 6 7 8 9. So I can have a cost which is
the cost of traveling from C6 from node
6 to 3. Right? And the co cost I'm
assuming here is symmetric. It doesn't
have to be symmetric.
streets are you know
>> what time is it?
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. So given these costs what is the
value now?
Anybody?
>> Cost.
>> Mhm. What is the value for each of these
nodes?
>> The cost from one point to the other.
>> The cost of one point to the other. No.
If you're speaking someone say profit,
right? So how would you define the
profit?
>> Reward cost reward minus cost.
>> Reward minus cost. Is there only one
cost to get from here to here?
>> No.
>> So h
>> the sum of which costs
>> the
>> lanes that we have used. Suppose I
choose to go this way
>> because
right would I do that?
>> Why would I not do that?
>> Want to go the shortest path.
>> Okay. Now what is the value of a node?
>> The the minimum cost maximum reward,
right? Of all the possible choices you
can make, you're going to find the one
that gets you the most money. That is
the value of any particular state,
right? And so that's where you uh
that's what you'd assign to each of
these guys. The notion of a value,
right? If I'm a cab company and if I'm
trying to do I have cabs at every
corner, which cab would I send?
>> How do you decide the closest one?
>> Shortest [snorts] distance.
>> Shortest. Which cab would I choose?
>> The the cab that's at the node with the
highest value. It's not just the
distance. There's a cost associated,
right? And so, we're going to say, okay,
you know what? This this distance is
very short, but there there's always a
traffic jam there. I'm going to spend a
gallon of gas. I can fly down this. So,
you know, I won't send this guy. I'm
going to send this guy. So, there's a
value, and you're going to assign the
cost, you know, the task to the cab at
the state with the highest value. But
now let's go back and you are a cab,
right?
If you are a cab out here,
you have a specific value, right?
But
knowing you don't know uh the optimal
path, you just know the value for your
node,
right? You can
uh
how do you decide which way are you
going to go?
You've been called by this person here.
You're at this node,
right? And you magically know the value
of every node.
>> Minimize. [clears throat]
>> Minimize how?
>> Well, if you know all the all values of
all
>> Yes.
>> then just choose the one that costs less
maximizes the value. So you want to say
that in terms of value.
>> Highest value.
>> You're going to go to the node with the
highest value. That's going to be the
direction in which you travel. What is
this?
>> It's a policy,
right? You're deciding which way to go.
And your policy is always going to be
you're looking at all of your neighbors.
You're picking the state which has the
highest value and you go and I'm going
to go towards it. a deterministic
policy, right? Does a deterministic
policy work every time
example where it doesn't work?
>> Um, well, this is pretty much greedy
search. So, sometimes even if you go to
the best one, the next step doesn't mean
it's going to be overall best.
>> The value, it's a value. It has to be
overall best by definition,
right? Because that value is considered
that.
So what is the property that we're
using? When I say that I only need to
look at my neighbors and I just pick the
one with the highest value.
What is the property I'm using?
>> No, I'm not speaking of that. What is
I'm assum making a specific assumption
that you know if I assign a value to
each of these guys
and do you know what the value is right
now? What did we say the value was?
cost
>> the the value was the profit you can
expect to make best case profit you can
expect to make from that node right and
so now if I
decide from here
all all I know are the values I don't
know the map I'm going to head out which
way would I go
to the one with the highest value the
next one with right Because
obviously you're increasing your every
time you make a step you're increasing
your value. You're you're not going to
go to something that actually is going
to cost you more because from there it
is going to cost you more. You're always
going to try to keep decreasing your
cost. Right?
What is the assumption that you have
made in this process?
>> The values aren't changing.
>> The values aren't changing. Right? Why
are the values not changing?
Because the end point is not moving.
>> The end point is not moving. There's a
model assumption over here. What was the
model assumption?
>> It's a mark of assumption that the cost
only depends on where you are and not
how you got here.
Right? If coming down this way changes
the value for whatever reason, maybe
because there's a a traffic light and
you're not allowed to do a U-turn or
whatever else, right? right? Or you're
not allowed to turn right at some point.
Uh if you come from here, you're not
allowed to turn right. But if you come
from here, you're allowed to turn left.
If you've been at the junction of uh
Morwood and and and the fifth and fifth,
you know that the value of that junction
depends on where you come from, which
direction you come from, right? And so
the value is not fixed in that case. The
value depends you some turns are not
allowed. So in that case, would I have a
fixed value for every node?
Is that Marov?
The Marco assumption is that the v you
know the future depends on where you are
and not how you got there.
It's a metaphor for life, right? Uh
would that be valid at the junction of
fifth and
I'm at the junction. Can I go anywhere?
No. What does it depend on?
>> Where I come from, right? So,
>> dude, I could not sleep. some
>> guys. You got to mute yourself, right?
So So is that Marov?
>> No, but you can make
>> because where you came from matters. Uh
>> you can make it.
>> How do you make it Marco?
>> Change the state.
>> How do I change the state?
>> By defining not only as where you are
but where you've come from. So if I if I
redefine my state and say my state is
not my intersection
but it's the pair of intersections where
I started from starting and where I
ended up at. Now that's captured a
junction right that's that's captured a
direction. And so here if I redefine my
states as 56
you know uh 63
right uh how many of such states would I
have in this case?
How many of such states would I have?
Look at the figure and tell me
how many states do I have if I define my
state as intersections?
>> 18. [clears throat]
>> I have nine states. Correct? If I have
uh uh if I define my states as
intersections. But if I define my states
as an ordered pair of where I started
from and where I got to, how many states
do I have?
>> 24 explain
>> every edge and you count twice
>> every edge going twice I can go from
here to here or from here to here right
I've increased the number of states but
now is it markoff
if all that matters is the direction now
it's marov right because all I need to
know that is I'm in this five six state
and that decides where I go Right?
But suppose for some reason there's some
city law which tracks you through two
junctions through two intersections.
Would this be mark of?
>> No.
>> But can it be made mark of by looking at
triplets? Right? So even if there's a
history factor to it by redefining your
state to account for the history you
took something that doesn't look like
marov and merit marov right so there's a
definition difference between the
information state which is the state
space in which you are marov and the
world space state which is where you
really are but as far as we are
concerned we can always think of the
world as being marov because you can
redefine my states in this manner. So
long as the uh not always but more often
than not if the hor if the amount that
you have to look back to decide where
you can go is finite then you can
redefine your whole process as Marco. So
that's why we live in Marco worlds. All
of everything that we do is defined in
terms of marov processes because for all
practical purposes anything can be
defined as marco. You just blow up the
state space. Right? So coming back over
here we had a policy and the policy we
assumed it was marco in a marov world
the values don't change
based on
you know where you came from but are you
going to be defining values over here or
over here where will you be defining
values now
on this guy right you're always going to
be defining values not on the world
state but on the on the
information state, right? That's the
Marco world where everything is going to
be defined. Okay? Uh you see how this
this gets complex very quickly, right?
So now over here,
[clears throat] let's just assume stay
with this because we know the world can
be Marco. What would be a good policy
over here? You're always going to go
towards the something that's increasing
your value, right?
But
let's just say that you have no idea
what's going to happen over here.
Out here
you have something random going on.
There's some un non This is Pittsburgh.
The non-zero probability. Hey, it
happens to me all the time. I just turn
left from my home. I'm faced with a guy
in an orange vest who asks me to go
back. Right. So or makes me go left or
right and I have no idea when it's going
to happen. Right? This happens all the
time. So here uh once I come down here
there's a probability
of being going of going down any which
way right so in that case are you still
going to go down just to the state with
the lowest value
highest value. What are you going to do?
>> Explore. No but what would your policy
be? Right. Firstly, what is the
assigned? You do you just use the value
just we just had or are you going to
have to redefine your value to account
for this randomness?
>> You're going to have to redefine the
value for this randomness. How do you
redefine the value for this randomness?
>> Hafest
path.
>> Safest path. No, you have to account for
the randomness in the process. Correct?
So here, let's say I have the value over
here
and here I have my
right here, right? I have my guys in my
orange vest. They're sending me any
which way. They could send me this way
with a probability of 1/3, this way with
a probability of 1/3, this way with a
probability of 1/3. Then the value over
here is the value here times 1/3. It's
the expected value over all possible
combinations, right?
So the V at any state
is going to be whatever local cost you
have at that state because you're going
to be waiting there, right? So I'll call
it the cost of the reward in that state
plus the summation over S prime
the other states that you can go to of
the probability of going from state S to
S prime times the value of S prime.
Right?
So you can't actually know your values.
You're going to now this is a set of
formula that you're going to have to
work through. You're going to iterate.
If all I know are these probabilities,
you're going to have to go back. You
know, each morning you set out in
traffic. You listen to the traffic
reports. The traffic reports tell you
about where the various intersections
where uh crazy things are happening. And
now you're going to go back and have to
reestimate the values for all the nodes
because that's how you're going to
determine the policy. You'll still
follow the policy of going to the node
with the best value except the manner in
which you computed the value changes.
Right? This guy did this equation make
sense.
Did this equation make sense to you
guys? That's the Bellman equation.
That's what we began with, right? the
value at any node. So now you can expand
this and say you know uh that there's a
cost with associated with every action.
So first
how do how do we actually define these
things for you to come up with an
optimal policy for what works and what
does not you need to know the values for
all the states right and uh if the state
space is small maybe you can work
through the mathematics
but even if you're working in Manhattan
driving in Manhattan where there are
finite number of
you know intersections
but the rules of turning can be
arbitrarily complex even though you may
only have like 300 intersections then
the state space can be of the order of
millions right so you can't really be uh
dealing with all of that but how let's
go back and look at how you would
actually store this information I can
say I have all of these states let's
let's still keep thinking of my
intersections as states then I can just
say uh state one state two state three
v1 1 v_sub_2 v3 and then you end up at a
new intersection that you've never seen.
How do you know its value?
You don't, right? But this look like
something familiar.
There's a state. I can define it anyhow
using all the features. There's a value.
Now this is a function from all the
known states and their values. I can
learn this function. Now I can apply
this function to newer states that I've
never encountered. And that's where the
entire that's where neural networks come
into the whole picture. I'm well out of
time. Let's stop right here. But yeah,
thank you guys.
[applause]